Finding Aid for Housing Division (University of Michigan) publications, 1923-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Housing Division (University of Michigan) publications 1923-2003, 1974-1996
University of Michigan. Housing Division.
10 linear feet
0357, Bimu, B6, 2
Publications produced by the Housing Division and its subunits, includes miscellaneous annual reports, brochures, bulletins, calendars, directories, manuals, newsletters, programs, reports, schedules, and statistics of the Housing Division and its predecessors, the Housing Office, Office of Student Community Relations, Office of the Director of Residence Halls, and Office of University Housing. Also includes printed materials from Department of Residence Education, Family Housing, Food Service, Housing Conference Services, Housing Facilities Department, Off-Campus Housing Program, the Pilot Program/College Community Program, and Residence Halls Libraries, and Housing Special Programs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (Donor no. 8160 ).
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The publications are open without restriction.
For historical note, please consult manuscripts finding aid for Housing Division (University of Michigan) records.
The Housing Division Publications (10 linear feet) include annual reports, brochures, bulletins, directories, ephemera (including flyers, invitations, posters, and programs), a history, manuals, newsletters, proceedings of conferences sponsored by the Housing Division, and reports. These publications are divided into three series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, and Topical Publications. The Housing Division publications document the broad responsibilities of this office and its sub-units, including the various housing options, such as family housing, off-campus housing, and residence halls; as well as food and dining services, mediation services, Residence Halls Association, Residence Halls Libraries, and various university housing task forces. Publications of individual residence halls are part of the sub-unit series.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Housing Division.; University of Michigan. Housing Office.; University of Michigan. Office of Student Community Relations.; University of Michigan. Housing Office.; University of Michigan. Food Service.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Residence Education.; University of Michigan. Family Housing.; University of Michigan. Off-Campus Housing Program.; University of Michigan. Housing Facilities Dept.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs.; Dormitories.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Housing Office.; University of Michigan. Office of Student Community Relations.; University of Michigan. Housing Office.; University of Michigan. Food Service.; University of Michigan. Housing Facilities Dept.; University of Michigan. Pilot Program/College Community Program.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Residence Education.; University of Michigan. Family Housing.; University of Michigan. Off-Campus Housing Program.
Genre Terms:
Brochures.; Bulletins.; Calendars.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Programs.; Reports.; Schedules (time plans); Statistics.; Student publications.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Housing Division. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
  The Unit Publications series (4.8 linear feet) includes scattered annual reports dating from 1940 to 1987 with the bulk of the reports from 1940 to 1950 and 1969 to 1987. Brochures include information about apartment leases, costs for student housing, Michigan Learning Communities, off-campus housing, and Spring-Summer housing. The bulletins document all aspects of housing both on campus and off, including campus housing from 1978 to 1984. These bulletins include descriptions of the various dormitories and other residence programs, such as language houses, Honors Program, or specialized housing such as the Lawyers Club or Martha Cook residences. The Living at Michigan bulletins discuss the various dormitories and residence programs as well as roommates, meal plans, and disabilities and special medical conditions.
  The directories include residence education staff directories dating from 1980 to 1990. These directories list the resident directors and advisors for each dorm on campus. The Residence Hall Telephone Directories list each student residing in the residence halls, their address and telephone number. These directories cover 1990 and 1993 through 1995. There are job descriptions of positions available to students within the Housing Division. They document the period from 1987 to 1993.
  This series contains a history of the division The Housing of Students, published in 1979. This booklet is divided into three sections with contributions by Peter A. Ostafin (Residence Halls for Men: The Michigan House Plan, from The University of Michigan, an Encyclopedic Survey, 1958), (Ruth Gjelsness (Housing of Women Students from The University of Michigan, an Encyclopedic Survey, 1958), and Edward C. Salowitz (Later Years: Physical Growth and Expansion, from The University of Michigan, an Encyclopedic Survey, 1979). It provides a comprehensive view of housing at the University of Michigan focusing on the programmatic aspects of housing, only incidentally touching on the construction of housing units.
  There is an extensive collection of manuals arranged alphabetically by title. These include handbooks for student athletes and coaches covering the period from 1988 to 1992. These manuals are entitled The Housing Division and Student Athletes published from 1988 to 1990 and Athletic Department/Housing Division Handbook: A Resource Guide for the Athletics Department Coaches and Staff issued in 1991 and 1992. The Bulletin of Information: Residence Halls Policies and Procedures, covering the period from 1976 to 1983 and 1993 to 1996, gives detailed information on alcohol abuse prevention, non-discrimination policies, parking, as well as, housing leases, and procedures governing meal tickets, payments, and student records. The Community Living at Michigan ([1994/95]-1998/99) describes the judicial procedures for students living in the residence halls including the Michigan Philosophy, the resident Bill of Rights, the community living standards, and lease terms and conditions. For earlier information about the student code of contact consult the Residence Hall Judicial Process: A Handbook for Students (1993/94) found under the heading "Office of Student Relations." There are also manuals dealing with crisis intervention, discrimination, safety and security, and sexual assault intervention. In addition, the researcher will find guides to residence hall education, programming, and move-in information.
  Newsletters include the Housing Bulletin, published from 1972 to 1992 for the residents of the various dormitories and the staff of the housing division. This newsletter includes information about the university in general and specific information about housing in particular, including articles about security, safety, special programs, research findings, and historical tidbits about the university. The Housing Bulletin's special Diversity Day editions, dated 1989 through 1993, are also included. Leased-Wise was published from 1975 to 1993 to help foster communication with the off-campus community. The articles focused on that community's concerns with discussions of tenant tax rebates, mediation services, health service, security deposits, and subletting.
  Reports include the 1983 report of the Alcohol Task Force regarding the role of the Housing Division in the prevention of alcohol abuse. In 1983 the Housing Division sponsored a survey to learn the needs and expectations of incoming students and to determine whether or not those needs were met. The results of this survey were published in an in-house publication entitled The 1983 Residence Halls Survey: Preliminary Report. There are numerous other reports, statistics, and surveys describing the development and history of the residence halls and other university-owned housing as well as the services offered by the Housing Division.
  - Announcements
    - 1992-1995 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports
    - 1940-1950 (Box 1)
    - 1969-1987 (Box 1)
    - Service Enterprises Annual Report, 1951-1955 (Box 1)
    - Student Residences: Statement of Revenue and Expense, 1968/69 (Box 1)
  - Articles
    - The Michigan House Plan, by Karl Litzenberg, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Bond Resolutions
    - 1967, 1970, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - Apartments (includes lease information) undated (Box 1)
    - Conference Information 1968-1971 (Box 1)
    - Costs for Student Housing 1986-1989 (Box 1)
    - Deposits 1986-1989 (Box 1)
    - Early Arrival Program, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Housing undated (Box 1)
    - Guest Information undated (Box 1)
    - Housing, undated (Box 1)
    - Jobs undated (Box 1)
      (describes student employment opportunities within Housing Division)
    - Lease Packets 1985-1989 (Box 1)
    - Mediation Services, 1973, undated (Box 1)
    - Michigan Learning Communities, 1998/99, 2002 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1957-1995, undated (Box 1)
    - North Campus Area Housing, 1986-1989 (Box 1)
    - Off-Campus Housing, 1964-1989 (Box 1)
    - Optional Meal Contracts, 1971-1981, undated (Box 1)
    - Residence Hall Lease Information 1989/90, 1998/99 (Box 1)
    - Residence Hall Neighborhoods, 1999, 2001 (Box 1)
    - Roommates 1986-1989 (Box 1)
    - Spring--Summer Housing, 1968-1979, 1989, 1993-1995 (Box 1)
    - Student Housing, 1965-1993, undated (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - Bulletin of Information: University Housing, 1968-1971 (Box 1)
    - Campus Housing, 1978-1984 (Box 1)
    - Living at Michigan, 1971-1980, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Residence Halls, 1978-1995, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Spring/Summer, 1971-1994 (Box 2)
    - Student Housing at the University of Michigan, 1965-1971, undated (Box 2)
  - Calendars
    - Living at Michigan: Guidelines for Community Living, 1983-1991 (Box 2)
  - Contracts
    - Contract for Residence: Terms and Conditions, 1967-1969 (Box 2)
  - Directories
    - Residence Halls 1980-1984 (Box 2)
    - Residence Education Staff Roster, 1984-1990, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Residence Halls Telephone Directory
      - 1990 1993 (Box 2)
      - 1994-1995, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Flyers
    - 1972-1995 (Box 2)
  - Histories
    - The Housing of Students, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Invitations
    - 1984-1991 (Box 2)
  - Job Descriptions
    - Come Join Our Staff: Residence Hall Staff Overview and Job Descriptions, 1987/88 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1993 (Box 2)
  - Manuals
    - Athletic Department/Housing Division Handbook: A Resource Guide for the Athletics Department Coaches and Staff, 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - Bulletin of Information: Residence Halls Policies and Procedures
      - 1976-1983 (Box 2)
      - 1989 1993-1996 (Box 2)
    - Codes and Regulations Applicable to the University of Michigan Housing Units, 1970 (Box 2)
    - Community Living at Michigan: Residence Halls Rules, Regulations and Policies, Judicial Process, [1994/95]-1998/99 (Box 2)
    - Closing/Opening Guides
      - Fall Term Closing/Winter Term Opening, 1992/93-1993/94 (Box 3)
      - Guide to Spring/Summer Closing and Fall Opening, 1993 (Box 3)
      - A Guide to Summer Term Closing/Fall Term Opening, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
      - Guide to Winter Term Closing and Spring/Summer Opening, 1993-1994 (Box 3)
    - Crisis Intervention and Security Information Manual--Housing Security, [ca. 1989] (Box 3)
    - Don't Be a Crime Statistic/If You Become a Crime Statistic, undated (Box 3)
    - Everything You Didn't Want to Know About Residence Halls* *But Were Afraid to Ask, 1971-1975 (Box 3)
    - Guidelines for Community Living--Rules, Regulations, Policies and Procedures, 1990-1994 (Box 3)
    - Guidelines for Staff Recruitment and Selection for 1978-79, 1978/79 (Box 3)
    - Housing at Michigan: An Orientation Guide for Parents, 1991 (Box 3)
    - The Housing Division and Student Athletes, 1988-1990 (Box 3)
    - Housing Division Staff Training: Housing Division Policy on Discrimination and Discriminatory Conduct (Handouts), 1990 (Box 3)
    - How to Succeed as a Student Employee without Really Trying: Housing Office University of Michigan Student Employee Policy Booklet, 1972/73 (Box 3)
    - In-Residence Staff Guide to Academic Information, 1974/75-1976/77 (Box 3)
    - Living at Michigan: Campus Housing, 1982/83 (Box 3)
    - Living at Michigan: An Orientation Guide for Parents, 1991/92-1994/95 (Box 3)
    - Living at Michigan: Residence Halls, General Information & Guidelines, 1998/99 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous 1988-1998 (Box 3)
    - The Programmer: A Resident Staff Guide to Resources and Facilitators--Residence Education, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Programming Handbook, 1970-1971, undated (Box 3)
    - Programming Resource Guide, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Reference Guide to Ann Arbor Housing, undated (Box 3)
    - Residence Hall Move-In, 1993-1994, 2000/01 (Box 3)
    - Sexual Assault Intervention Handbook: A Section of the University of Michigan Housing Division Residence Staff Manual, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Student Employee Handbook, 1984-1990 (Box 3)
    - Student Employee Survival Kit, 1974-1982 (Box 3)
    - Welcome to University Housing, undated (Box 3)
  - Maps
    - Apartments for Married Students and Staff Members, undated (Box 3)
    - Guide to Your Central Campus Residence Hall, 1994 (Box 3)
    - Housing Information Map, 1973-1992 (Box 3)
    - Off-Campus Housing, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters
    - Associated Housing News and Views, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Guards Gazette, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Houseline, 1981-1986 (Box 3)
    - Housing Bulletin, 1972-1992, 21 folders (Box 4)
    - Housing Bulletin, Special Edition--Diversity Day, 1989-1993 (Box 4)
    - Housing News and Views, 1971 (Box 4)
    - Housing Newsletter, 1974/75 vol. 7 (Box 4)
    - Leased Wise, 1975-1993, 12 folders (Box 4)
    - News-Link, 1992-1993, 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    - Options, 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - Residence Halls Safety
      - Volumes 1-7 (scattered) 1968-1974 (Box 4)
    - Staff Bulletin: News and Views, 1968-1974, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Strategic Communicator, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Posters
    - 1998/99 (Box 4)
  - Press Releases
    - Announcement, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Proceedings
    - Proceedings of the Sixteenth Annual Conference of the Association of College and University Housing Officers Held at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI, August 2-5, 1964, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Programs
    - Resident Staff Training Conference 1988 (Box 4)
  - Proposals
    - A Proposal for a Residence Hall Based Academic Counseling Program, 1974 (Box 4)
  - Prospectus
    - Potential Sites: Proposed Single Student Housing, 1971 (Box 4)
  - Questionnaire
    - PEC Questionnaire, 1978 (Box 5)
  - Reports
    - Alcohol Task Force, [1983] (Box 5)
    - An Explanation of the Area Concept for University Housing at the University of Michigan, undated (Box 5)
    - Housing Systems: Detail Systems Design Specification, 1979 (Box 5)
    - International Student Housing Problems and Opportunities at the University of Michigan, 1990 (Box 5)
    - Living-Learning Programs at the University of Michigan, August 1996 (Box 5)
    - Reach Out '93: Final Report, 1993 (Box 5)
    - Revising Eligibility Requirements in Family Housing at the University of Michigan, circa 1991 (Box 5)
    - Transition Team #1, undated (Box 5)
    - University Housing at the University of Michigan:
      - Program Review, a Self-Assessment Based on Council for the Advancement of Standards Guidelines and Standards, 1997 (Box 5)
      - Strategic Plan, 1996-2009 A Report to University Housing Staff, 1997 (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan [a report from the Facilities Management Evaluation Program], 1993 (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan and Michigan State Universities: A Comparison of Residence Hall Room and Board Rates, 1997 (Box 5)
  - Schedules
    - Payment Schedules: Residence Halls and Family Housing, 1948-1999 (Box 5)
  - Speeches
    - Staff Role: Specific Expectations of the Resident Directors and Resident Advisors..., 1969 (Box 5)
  - Statistics
    - Housing Division Fact Kit, 1992-1994, undated (Box 5)
    - Housing Information, 1949-1992 (Box 5)
    - Residence Hall Rates, 1940-1993 (Box 5)
    - University Housing Historical and Building Data, 1982, 1986, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Surveys
    - Exit Survey. 1989 (Box 5)
    - The 1983 Residence Halls Survey: Preliminary Report, [1983] (Box 5)
    - Resident Satisfaction Survey, 1993, 1995-1996, 3 folders (Box 5)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs, and organizations within the Housing Division. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit.
  The Sub-Unit Publications series (5.1 linear feet) includes publications from Housing Division sub-units, such as Department of Residence Education, Family Housing, Food Service, Housing Facilities Department, Off-Campus Housing Program, the Pilot Program/College Community Program, the individual residence halls and the Residence Halls Association, Residence Halls Libraries, the Twenty First Century Program, and the Women in Science and Engineering Residence Program. These offices within the Housing Division published annual reports, brochures, manuals, and newsletters documenting their functions.
  The family housing bulletins (scattered issues from 1977 to 1995) include floor plans of the various apartments with application, lease, and community information. Family Housing News (1979-1982) and The Community Focus newsletter (1981-1995) document the activities of and programs for the residents, and help keep residents informed about policy and personnel changes in the Housing Division.
  The Housing Facilities Department publications include annual reports (1985-1996) documenting projects like asbestos management, carbon monoxide detection, radon testing, lead paint removal, and other health concerns. These reports also include information about housing utilities and energy usage and housing goals to conserve water and energy. The appendices include a staff list and a building inventory including square footage, year first occupied, original cost, and replacement cost of each dorm. The Energy Report (1978/79) and the Utilities and Energy Management Report (1979-1986) break-down natural gas, electricity, water and steam usage for the year and compare them to years past. They also compare consumption by individual dormitory.
  The Housing Special Programs works closely with minority students on campus. The Ethnic Reflections anthology, containing poetry and short essays, was published from 1979 to 1988.
  The Off-Campus Housing bulletins (1964-1995) describe where and how to look for housing, housing options such as Greek houses or co-ops, costs, renters' rights, and agencies to contact if there are problems. There are brochures describing the fraternities and sororities on campus. The Safety and Sanitation Manual for Small Group Houses gives students advice on how to take care of the homes they are renting including tips on cleaning, maintenance, decorating, city regulations, etc. The report Student Housing: Report of the President's Off-Campus Housing Commission is found under the heading "President's Commission on Off-Campus Housing."
  Additional publications documenting the student judicial process including offenses, sanctions, and the appeal process will be found under the heading "Office of Student Relations." These manuals (1993/94) also include the Statement of Student Rights and Responsibilities.
  Created in 1962, the Pilot Program is a living/learning program allowing students to take courses, averaging 15-25 students, taught in their dormitories. The Pilot Program publications include annual reports, brochures, and bulletins covering the period from 1970 to 1995. Of special interest are the publications created by the students and resident employees of the various dorms. Found under the heading "Residence Halls' these publications include anthologies, brochures, manuals and handbooks, and newsletters. All residence halls are represented. Newberry will be found with Barbour and West Quad. Among the Residence Halls Libraries publications there are annual reports (1960-1993 scattered), manuals describing policies and procedures (1966-1985), and a report of the Library Selection Committee (1964).
  Created in May 1989, the University Task Force on Faculty, Staff and Student Housing Issues released their interim and final reports in 1990. The task force mission was to study the university's role with regard to undergraduate, graduate, faculty, and staff housing, and its relationship to the broader Ann Arbor community, and to recommend how the university could enrich the educational and community-building potential of the housing environment. The interim reports and final report include results of surveys taken by students and faculty, discussion of the development of senior faculty and staff housing, Greek organizations, minority housing, and public hearing commentary on various housing issues.
  - Conference Management and Hospitality Services
    - Annual Reports 1990/91-1992/93 (Box 5)
    - Brochures 1992-1995 (Box 5)
    - Newsletters
      - Keeping in Touch, 1994-1997, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Conference Management Services
    - Annual Reports 1995/96 (Box 5)
  - Conferences and Seminars Office
    - Brochures undated (Box 5)
  - Department of Residence Education
    - Brochures 1989-1990 (Box 5)
    - Manuals
      - Resident Staff Selection: Guidelines and Procedures with Job Descriptions
        - 1990-1991 (Box 5)
        - 1993 (Box 5)
    - Newsletters
      - ResEd Times, 1995 (Box 5)
  - Dining Services
    - Strategic Plan 1991/92 (Box 5)
  - Family Housing
    - Brochures undated (Box 6)
    - Bulletins
      - Family Housing, 1977-1995 (scattered issues), 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Newsletters
      - The Community Focus, 1981-1999 vol. 1-16, 17 folders (Box 6)
      - Family Housing News, 1979-1982 (Box 6)
    - Reports
      - Family Housing Report, undated (Box 6)
    - Special Programs
      - Child Development Center undated (Box 6)
      - Language Program 1994, undated (Box 6)
      - Northwood
        - Newsletters
          - Northwood IV News, 1977 (Box 6)
          - The Undaily, 1968-1974, 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Food Service
    - Brochures
      - Meal Plans 1971-1992, undated (Box 7)
    - Manuals
      - Student Employee Policy Booklet, 1972-1973, undated (Box 7)
    - Newsletters
      - Entree Plus Press, 1991 (Box 7)
      - Just for "U", 1982 (Box 7)
      - Tete-a-Tete, 1992-1993, undated (Box 7)
    - Reports
      - A Feasibility Study for the Consolidation of the Food Service Areas in Couzens, Alice Lloyd, Mosher-Jordan and Stockwell Dormitories, 1978 (Box 7)
  - Hospitality Services
    - Strategic Plan 1990 (Box 7)
  - Housing Catering
    - Menus 1994 (Box 7)
  - Housing Conference Services
    - Brochures undated (Box 7)
  - Housing Facilities Department
    - Annual Reports
      - 1985-1996, 4 folders (Box 7)
      - Energy Report, 1978/79 (Box 7)
      - Utilities and Energy Management Report, 1979-1986, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Manuals
      - Facilities Council Handbook, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Housing Information Office
    - Listings
      - Faculty and Staff Housing Referrals, 1995-1997 (Box 7)
  - Housing Research Office
    - Reports